[Anita] Hi all! thank you very much for
joining us for this week's MagNetZ!
as usual our seminar format is about 25
minutes presentation during which you can
keep your microphone muted and after that we're
going for 15 minutes question discussion
you can use the chat or you can unmute yourself
and ask the question, and at the end of this
there is a part that is not recorded is a time for
an informal catch. So i'm really happy today to
present them to present here Yoichi Usui for
Kanazawa University Japan who is going to present
the title "Three or five components of magnetic
mineralogy of Cenozoic pelagic sediment in the
North Pacific". Please feel free to share
your screen, the floor is yours. [Usui] Thank you
okay, let me start uh today i will talk about
environmental magnetism or pelagic sediments
and try to convince you that the major
variation can be described by three components.
sorry
First I introduce a background motivation. During
Cenozoic global climate change show changes in
various time scales. There is a general cooling
trend and several shutdown marks and coolings
then the last few million years is characterized
by large oscilations associated with glacial cycles.
The north Pacific has been affected also by
regional changes especially in central Asia.
Particularly relevant to sediment magnetism
is aeolian input from central Asia.
The non-specific has been increased and dust flux
has been observed at around 25 Ma and probably
around 3.5 to 2 Ma. Each of them may correspond
to increased rhd in central Asia or global cooling.
In conventional environmental magnetism signals
are detected by single-valued proxies such as
s-ratios. More recently it has become common to
consider more than one more than two magnetic
components in single samples. This has enabled
detailed discussions but at the same time a mixing
into more than two components is often non-unique.
One way to reduce the ambiguity is to compare
multiple sites to extract general pattern and
that is what I would like to present today.
First I introduce uh sorry,
quickly I show the sites I will mention
today these are in north uh west Pacific.
Today I will not discuss much about their
chronology simply because uncertainty is
so large, but basically the core bottoms are
thought to be rarly paleogene or even Cretaceous,
but there may be hiatus or considerable variations
in sedimentation rates so care should be taken
to convert depth variation into age progression.
I will proceed along this diagram, first
using simple analysis and then with more
complicated techniques. I should stress
that today I try to capture the first
order features. I believe detailed study of a site
can recover more components than I present today.
First let's look at the division
between biogenic and terrigenous components.
These days it is near a common
sense that sediments often contain
magnetofossils and this also
applies to a pelagic red clay.
These graphs show ARM
susceptibility over SIRM.
This quantity takes the highest value
for non-interacting single domain grains
and for magnetite the value can reach up
to around three millimeter per Ampere.
Magnetostatic interactions and larger grain
size would reduce the value. All examined site
part or part of all examined sites show a very high
value up to 2.5 or 2.7 and this can only be
explained by the dominance of non-interacting
SD grains. At the same time the range of the values
indicate mixing of at least two components, one
is no interrupting SD and the other is not. The
simplest interpretation is that non-interacting
SD component reflects magneto fossils.
Now an interesting question is whether there is
a variation within the magnetofossil
component because it is well known that different
magnetic bacteria live in different environment
which can also be a paleoenvironmental proxies.
The above 3 graphs shows simple IRM acquisition
gradients for magnetofossil-rich samples selected
based on high ARM susceptibility. As you see
even though these are from different sites
they are remarkably similar to each other.
Moreover if I decompose some samples
with a moderate ARM susceptibility value,
like this one, and then I obtain a one
magnetofossil component, here labeled as C4
which also shows similar coercivity and
dispersion, to the above magnetofossil-rich samples.
Furthermore, these samples including the one
with moderate ARM susceptibility, contain
a biogenic magnetite of very similar
size and shape under TEM observations.
So I propose that pelagic red clay contain
a single magnetofossil component
coming from this equivalent octahedral
magnetite. As I emphasized I propose this
as a first order feature and i will also
discuss some exceptions later in this talk.
We have seen this octahedral biogenic magnetite
so now we move to the subdivision
of the terrigenous component.
Again let me start from something simple. This
is a cross plot of s-ratio for 100 milli Tesla
and karm over SIRM. Magnetosomes
would plot somewhere here.
Because these quantities are both normalized by
SIRM, mixing of two components would produce a
straight line on this plot but I think
these data show more complex pattern
suggesting it is not simple a single biogenic
and single terrigenous component, a mixing.
I thought, sorry, I suggest these data can
be interpreted in this way. From one
low coercivityy terrigenous component,
one line connects to a magnetofossils
and there is another line extend
to a lower s-ratio, in other words
higher coercivity. But terrigenous components may have
similar ARM susceptibility and the multiple
components may plot on this line so from this
data alone I cannot say.. I can only say there are
more than two more than one terrigenous
component in the north Pacific pelagic clays.
At the same time this conclusion is rather robust
so require more than one terrigenous component.
To get further information I study
one site, ODP site 777, more closely.
This site has rough age constraints
from a site report, as these ones.
And this site also shows
high ARM susceptibility
in the deeper part of the core and lower ARM
susceptibility in the upper part of the core.
This interval is expected to contain a
less biogenic component and the age is
back to around 12 Ma. IRM acquisition curves
of this interval shows..is shown here
and they show increase in coercivity in
the core top, from around 6 meter depth.
The structure of this variation is examined by
a principal component analysis. The variance is
explained by a three-dimensional PC space PC1
PC2 and PC3. The colors show depths of the samples.
The data points in the PC space show a linear
trend down to around 6.25 meter,
and then cluster below this dephts.
And the trend towards a cluster, expressed in
this orange line, probably shows increasing
biogenic component to the deeper part of
the core. And another line here, blue line,
suggests the mixing of two terrigenous components,
because biogenic component is somewhere here.
Unlike ARM susceptibility, we expect
distinct IRM acquisition curves for
different terrigenous components, so a linear
trend here suggests that most of the variation
can be explained by two terrigenous components,
although it wouldn't exclude additional components.
The start of this trend is at 6.25
meters which probably is around
2 Ma, give or take. Between 2 and 12 Ma data
are here so the variation may be explained by
simply increasing biogenic contribution without
the need of additional terrigenous components.
I did similar analysis on another site,
northeast from the site 777. This core shows a
low ARM susceptibility throughout, suggesting
smaller contribution of biogenic magnetite,
and the age of the core is estimated by a
paleomagnetism and the bottom of the core
is probably around 2 million years ago.
At first look the IRM acquisition curve
is explained.. it is explained.. by a two
trends in principal component space.
but in fact when I look at the depths variation of
principal components PC2, shown in red here, shows
variation in rather restricted part of the core,
which I think corresponds to a volcanic ash.
So the majority of the data is actually explained
by a simple two.. a simple linear trend to
component mixing and again the depth trend
suggests that increasing contribution of
higher coercivity component towards the
lower part and shallower part of the core.
Paleomagnetism gives these age a constraints
so the data from this site also support
that from around 2 Ma there is an
increasing contribution of the higher
coercivity terrigenous component against
lower uh coercivity terrigenous component.
Actually this pattern is consistent with a
classical work by a Yamazaki and Yoka reporting
increasing coercivity from around 2 million
years ago, at that time involved from s-ratios.
Back then they interpreted the trend by mixing
between one biogenic and one terrigenous component,
but present analysis suggests
that the change within
terreigenous fraction may be more
important to explain this pattern.
So, so far we have seen the basic three components:
the octahedral magnetite are everywhere,
the higher coercitivy component
has become important from around 2 Ma,
and a lower coercivity component is present at
least from 12 Ma. An obvious limitation is that
I cannot constrain how far back in time the
lower coercivity component is present. I think
the s-ratio versus ARM suscetivity plot
suggests that there is a only one a common low
correctivity component but the evidence is not so
strong. Also when biogenic magnetite was dominant,
probably before or 25 to 35 Ma, it is not easy
to characterize terrigenous magnetic component,
even with detailed unmixing techniques. So
it is unknown how far back this component
is stable and present in north pacific.
But for now
let me move on to some special components bullet
and a non-chain octahedra of biogenic magnetite.
Bullet-shaped magnetofossils has
been discovered from this site,
like those ones shown here.
I think we can speculate the meaning of
the bullet-shaped magnetite in two ways.
On the one hand, elongate magnetofossils have been
thought to represent less oxic condition
and so the presence of bullet-shaped magneto
fossils in deep-sea red clay may suggest that
these can be used as an
paleoenvironmental proxy.
On the other hand, morphology including the
presence of manganese oxide suggests that
the sediments have been oxic throughout so
the presence of this kind of magnetofossils
may suggest that factors other than oxygen
might control the morphology of magnetofossils.
I have spent some time to search for similar
magnetofossils in north Pacific red clay, but so
far I found..I haven't found any evidence.
This pattern.. this is another compilation of
data this time s-ratio for 100 meters and
its ratio for 30 meters because elongated
bullet-shaped magnetofossils has
higher coercivity than equivalent magnetofossils.
Such grains should plot towards lower.. upper
left of the plot but the only core showing
such trend shown, in red here, is actually
the core shown.. I have shown before.
So from this i conclude that bullet-shaped much
forces is rather an exception for pelagic red clay.
Another special component is non-chained magneto
follis. At ODP site 777 we found that for some
sample central ridge from the FORC diagram
has an apparent peak at around 10 milli tesla
in addition to a more common 30 tesla peak.
Because it is central ridge, this should come
from non-intaction single domain grains.
However this low coercivity 10 milli tesla is
almost equal to the theoretical value for
isotropic grain single domain and magnetite
crystal. Crystal elongation or chain formation
would significantly increase coercivity, so I think
the only explanation is to have isolated grains.
Curiously no difference in crystal morphology
of magnetic separates has been observed,
even for samples containing a large amount
of this peak. Therefore we conclude that this
signature is from isolated octahedral biogenic
magnetite, coexisting with chained crystals.
In contrast to the bullet-shaped
grains, I think the isolated
non-chained magnetofossils may be widespread.
I have shown these three plots to impress
the similarity between the size.. among the
site of the magnetofossils component, however
when I do component mixing these
could be a fitted by a combination of
high higher correctivity biogenic component
and a lower coercivity biogenic component,
which is very similar to the chained and
non-chain component observed in site 777.
In contrast to site 777, those sites do not show
significant depth variations of the low coercivity
part, so data from each site, when analyzed
individually, do not require a mixing of two
components. But the results from site 777 hint we
may look for the signal in different sites as well.
So this these are my conclusion. Firstly,
to a first order, a magnetism of clay in the
North Pacific can be explained by rather a
simple model of a mixture of three components,
and terrigempis components reflect
large scale eolian dust evolutions,
particularly from around two million
years ago, but the data before 12 Ma is
still insufficient and we should do more research
about that. The biogenic components may provide
deep sea environmental proxy but generally these
biogenic component is explained by chain octaedral
component, so systematic variation needs further
investigation. It is true that the chronology of
red clay is rather limited. At the same time one
of the strengths of magnetic measurement is that
we can scan a large number of samples compared to,
for example, chemical analysis, so I think we have
a good reasons to continue see for our research,
and that is a strategy. But I also welcome
questions and discussion about specific magnetic
components in this occasion, thank you very much
[Anita] thank you very much for your presentation Usuisan.
If there are questions from the audience
please type it in the chat or ask it. A big
round of applause around, thank you very much!
[Richard] I'll jump in with a question. Great talk,
really enjoyed it. What you're showing how..
I'm not too familiar with the sediment ends
of things..how widespread do you think this
multi-component mixing is? Is it
restricted to the North Pacific or do
you think this is something we're going
to be encountering anywhere you look?
[Usui] It's a great question. And the simple
answer is I'm not sure, but for
what i believe is for biogenic magnetite, I
think, it reflects a living environment for
bacteria and i think it's rather common to deep
sea clay, so you may find similar ones in Atlantic
Ocean or somewhere else. For all terrigenous
components I believe these are from mainly
central Asia so it's more restricted
to the North Pacific at this age.
[Richard] thanks, great!
[Anita] thank you thank you very much. there is a
question in the chat from Gunter, he says:
"nice work" and asks if "have you measure a frequency
dependent susceptibility on any of your samples"
[Usui] thank you for that question, but no,
I haven't. So I'm sorry for that. [Anita] thank you.
is there any other question
from the live audience?
Maybe there is no other question. Thank
you very much thank you oh..there is a there is..
yes please Shibuya-san, unmute yourself and
ask a question thank you [Shibuya] are there any
correlation between the remanence
goodness of remanence like that?
[Usui] generally speaking sediment with a higher
amount of terrigenous magnetite ..terrigenous
component.. it seems to be better in terms of
paleomagnetic recording, but I think it's more due
to higher sedimentation rate, because higher
fract..higher terrigenous components suggest
increased flux dust flux which is to higher
sedimentation rate. So I'm not so sure if
the remanence's goodness is directly related to
the magnetic components [Shibuya] well, thank you very much.
[Anita] thank you very much.
If there is other questions.. [Andrei] I have a question
but my my transmission might be complicated uh
is what is the red where is
the red color from what are the
red color of your pelagic clay
is it hematite or maghemmite?
[Usui] I don't know. First thing is it's generally
called red clay but the color is not really red
it's probably more like brown or dark brown color.
And I don't think there is a significant amount
of hematite but of course color is not quite
dependent on the amount so I'm don't..I'm
not so sure, but I think for example dark colour
is from manganese oxide partly and for it
no well, I don't think right
now I can specify the cause.
[Andrei] thank you [Anita] okay thank you very much.
Please remember that you can always
post questions also on the YouTube
channel if you have any other questions.
So if is there any other question..
okay, if there is no other question we
can give another big round of applause
to Usui-san. [Usui] Thank you
[Anita[ thank you very much for presenting to MagNetZ,
we're really, really happy. If you
could please unshare your screen,
I'm gonna share my screen
and this is to briefly tell you that we're gonna
keep this schedule for the summer, or summer in
our hemisphere, sorry. From June to August
27th of July we're gonna have Eric Font from
Lisbon, and we have another talk from Zheng-Xiang
Li 24th of us and we're gonna move back to
kind of western friendly times
from September to December. We're gonna
need more speakers, so please, if you want to give
a talk, please contact me or Greig or anybody from
team, and please also remember that all previous
MagNetZ, including this one, are available on
our YouTube channel.Yyou're welcome to like it,
and watch them, download them from the area as
well and thank you again forjoining us
to MagNetZ seminar! thank you very much!